<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Thomas Lutkus</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Thomas Lutkus</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.154.5</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 17:20:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Proxmox Lab (Part 3) - Scripting the Lab</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vlab_part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 17:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vlab_part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-introduction&#34;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;11-foreword&#34;&gt;1.1 Foreword&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last 2 weeks since I have started to write this series, I was asked a few times &amp;ldquo;what about&amp;rdquo; Ansible, Terraform and other automation tools. The easy answer is: they are besides the point of what I&amp;rsquo;m trying to achieve right now. When I learned to build a VMware cluster, I learned to build the virtualization platform first, and to understand the network topology and the whys. I think that good teaching builds toward something. This tutorial series is a lot about learning a builder&amp;rsquo;s mindset and learning how to put some things together. It&amp;rsquo;s not about a quick recipe for a ready-to-go thing. If I was aiming at just that, I could easily go to a &amp;ldquo;here&amp;rsquo;s the GitHub repo, here are the requirements and some basic instructions and off you go&amp;rdquo;. Or even &amp;ldquo;here&amp;rsquo;s the repo, go to your chatbot and figure it out&amp;rdquo;. Instead, I want the reader to see the struggles and feel the needs for certain tools. I&amp;rsquo;m also adding a lot of personal touch, like the way I&amp;rsquo;m doing the &lt;code&gt;~/libvirt&lt;/code&gt; directory. I like the idea of taking the chance to teach a new trick or two, or go into territory that most DevOps Engineers or SREs don&amp;rsquo;t go to. If you think about it, in this series I&amp;rsquo;m teaching how to build a virtualization cluster. I&amp;rsquo;m also excited to iterate on my network diagram designs, on the cluster design itself and for people to maybe see it and feel stoked to get into &amp;ldquo;learning the craft&amp;rdquo; through repetition and persistence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Proxmox Lab (Part 2) - Auto-Install Proxmox</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vlab_part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 19:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vlab_part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-introduction&#34;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we will be deploying an enterprise-grade lab. Therefore we need to think about how we do things in production: we can&amp;rsquo;t be clicking around and hoping for the best. This quickly compounds. We also need things to scale, to be idempotent (magic word for &amp;ldquo;always works the same&amp;rdquo;) and self-healing. As I see this series going right now, we will be iterating the design of our lab a little bit as we go, since there is always room for improving and learning. That being said, I have done some changes to Part 1 to keep things consistent with this new post, add some stuff and fix minor errors. You should check it out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Proxmox Lab (Part 1) - Setting up your Environment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vlab_part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 19:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vlab_part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-introduction&#34;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;11-lab-design&#34;&gt;1.1. Lab Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have some cool experience deploying and configuring a Proxmox cluster with High Availability and fully redundant Ceph in production. I thought it&amp;rsquo;d be cool to share my insights. Since I have been meaning to redeploy my lab on my laptop to test some things, I thought this is a good time. To start, this post will be about setting up the lab environment and install one Proxmox instance. I&amp;rsquo;m going to write a few other tutorials as I go. You are free to use the content here as you see fit. I would appreciate being credited, but that&amp;rsquo;s not a requirement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systemd Service Units</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/systemd-service-units/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 19:03:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/systemd-service-units/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systemd service units are files which define a service, and when/how it&amp;rsquo;s started. They will normally refer to a program or script to be executed. There are 3 fundamental sections on a service file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Unit]&lt;/code&gt; is where the description resides, as well as the conditions to initialize the service, such as requirements and dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Service]&lt;/code&gt; is where the parameters which determine how to run the service reside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Install]&lt;/code&gt; is how to enable the unit. It&amp;rsquo;s optional, but normally necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Have a Blog?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/why-have-a-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 16:16:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/why-have-a-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi there! I&amp;rsquo;m an infrastructure engineer with 15+ years of experience building and supporting Linux and network infrastructure. I built a team from scratch, I&amp;rsquo;m a &amp;ldquo;wear all hats&amp;rdquo; guy at my current job. More importantly, I&amp;rsquo;m a husband and father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is for sharing my knowledge and experiences in the tech industry. It&amp;rsquo;s also for writing thoughts and opinions. My hope is to express things which are meaningful and impactful. I also mean to write about technology and privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure engineer based in Ireland. 15+ years building and supporting Linux systems across enterprise environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve worked at AT&amp;amp;T, IBM, BT, Zalando, HelloFresh, TomTom, and VMware. Currently focused on virtualization Linux and Virtualization (Proxmox, RHEL), automation (Ansible), and security compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pursuing RHCSA and RHCE certifications in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog covers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical posts&lt;/strong&gt;: Linux administration, Ansible, Proxmox, shell scripting, problems I&amp;rsquo;ve solved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thinking posts&lt;/strong&gt;: Work ethics, privacy, technology and society, occasional philosophy with a Christian perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to write what I learn and my thoughts. No fluff, no engagement bait.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
